Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (34th: 1955) records 1955
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislative Assembly (34th: 1955) records
Montana Historical Society Archives
LR 34
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
1 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains the records (1955) of the Montana 34th Legislative Assembly including the minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, and joint resolutions and memorials; and miscellany.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 34th Montana Legislature met from January 3rd to March 3rd, 1955. The leaders of the Senate were George Gosman (R-President), and Glenn Larson (R-President Pro Tempore and Majority Leader). The leaders of the House were Leo Graybill (D-Speaker), John Emmons (D-Speaker Pro Tempore), and Eugene Mahoney (D-Majority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
The collection includes the minutes and reports of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, and resolutions; House Memorials (re amendment of NATO Status of Forces Treaty; dismantling Soil Conservation Service; federal price support program for farm commodities; and adjustment of federal farm program for growers of quality wheat); Senate Memorials (re the death of William R. Allen); and House and Senate joint memorials. The collection also contains miscellany material including a list of members of Senate Mines and Mining Committee.
The collection is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into one subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically).
The series House of Representatives is organized into six subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House Bills (arranged numerically), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), House Memorials (arranged numerically), House Joint Memorials (arranged numerically), and Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically).
The series Senate is organized into six subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Senate Memorials (arranged nalphabetically), Senate Joint Memorials (arranged numerically), and Status Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged choronologically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Montana--Committees.
Libby Dam (Mont.); Montana--Politics and government.; Yellowtail Dam (Mont.)
Montana.; Government and Politics.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Joint Committees
  - Joint Committee Minutes
    - [See Joint House Appropriations and Senate Finance Claims committees minutes in House Appropriations Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint House Appropriations Committee and Senate Finance Claims Subcommittee on the University System Budget minutes in Senate Finance and Claims Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations Committee minutes in House Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee minutes in House Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee minutes]
    - [See Joint House Ways and Means Committee minutes in House Ways and Means Committee minutes]
- House of Representatives
  - House Standing Committee Minutes
    - Affairs of Cities, 1955 January 13 - March 1 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Appropriations (includes Joint House Appropriations and Senate Finance and Claims committees), 1955 January 5 - March 2 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Aviation, 1955 January 25 - February 1 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Banking and Insurance, 1955 January 24 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Conservation and Development, 1955 January 13 - February 21 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations (includes Joint Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations Committee, February 7, 1955), 1955 January 25 - February 24 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Education, 1955 January 12 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Employment, 1955 January 3 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Fish and Games (includes report), 1955 January 12 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Highways and Highway Transportation, 1955 January 20 - March 3 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Irrigation and Water Conservation (includes Joint Irrigation and Water Conservation Committee, February 4, 1955), 1955 January 17 - February 23 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - Labor, 1955 January 13 - February 10 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Liquor Control, 1955 January 20 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
    - Livestock and Public Ranges, 1955 January 20 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - Military Affairs, 1955 January 17 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
    - Mines and Mining, 1955 February 11-15 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
    - Oil and Gas, 1955 January 13 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
    - Privileges and Elections, 1955 January 19 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
    - Public Health, Morals and Safety, 1955 January 19 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
    - Public Utilities and State Commissions (includes public hearing, February 10, 1955), 1955 January 27 - February 10 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
    - Railroads and Railway Transportation, 1955 January 25 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
    - Social Security, 1955 January 12 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - State Boards and Institutions, 1955 January 13 - February 22 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - State Lands, Forest and Parks, 1955 January 29 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - Townships and Counties, 1955 January 13 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - Ways and Means (includes Joint Ways and Means Committee, January 11, 1955), 1955 January 11 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - Workmen's Compensation, 1955 January 27 - February 14 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - House Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-3, 8-9, 11-13, 15-18, 20-23, 26, 29-36, 38-48, 50-53, 55-56, 58-59, 61-63, 66-67, 70, 72-73, 76-86, 88, 91-97, 101-107, 109-114, 116-117, 119-122, 125, 129-130, 132, 134-141, 144-150, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
    - Bill nos. 152-159, 161-163, 165, 167-173, 175-179, 183-185, 187-188, 190-192, 194, 196, 198-201, 203-204, 208, 210-211, 214-216, 218-232, 235, 237-239, 241-253, 255-257, 260, 262, 265-273, 276-281, 284-285, 288-289, 291, 293, 300, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
    - Bill nos. 301, 305-310, 312-314, 316-317, 319-327, 329-330, 332, 334, 337-338, 341-342, 344-352, 354, 359-360, 362, 367, 370-374, 377, 379, 383, 388, 390, 393-394, 396-397, 400-402, 404, 408, 410, 413, 417-424, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 30)
  - House Joint Resolutions
    - Bill nos. 1-2, 4, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 31)
  - House Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-4 (re amendment of NATO Status of Forces Treaty; dismantling Soil Conservation Service; federal price support program for farm commodities; and adjustment of federal farm program for growers of quality wheat), 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 32)
  - House Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-12 (re irrigation canal seepage, mosquito control, and land development; Charles M. Russell commemorative stamp; construction at Moorhead Dam site; long and short haul clauses of Interstate commerce Act; personal income tax credit exemption; development of topographic maps; control of diseases and harmful insects in forests; rehabilitation and education for landless Indians; construction of coal hydrogenation plant; contracts for services rendered on Indian reservations; addition of U.S. Highway 2 to interstate system; and status of Bob Marshall Wilderness Area), 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 33)
  - Status Sheets of House Bills
    - 42nd Legislative Day, 1955 February 13 (Box-folder 1 / 34)
- Senate
  - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
    - Agriculture, 1955 January 26 - February 23 (Box-folder 1 / 35)
    - Banks and Banking, 1955 January 27 - February 14 (Box-folder 1 / 36)
    - City and Town Affairs, 1955 January 14 - February 24 (Box-folder 1 / 37)
    - Constitutional Amendments and Federal Relations, 1955 January 20 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 38)
    - County Affairs, 1955 January 21 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 39)
    - Elections and Apportionment, 1955 January 24 - February 4 (Box-folder 1 / 40)
    - Education, 1955 January 13 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 41)
    - Finance and Claims (includes Joint and Senate Finance and Claims and House Appropriations committees, January 26 and February 9, 1955; and Joint Senate Finance and Claims Committee and House Appropriations Subcommittee on the University System Budget, January 17-18, 1955), 1955 January 5 - March 3 (Box-folder 1 / 42)
    - Fish and Game, 1955 January 12 - February 25 (Box-folder 1 / 43)
    - Indian Affairs, 1955 February 8 - March 1 (Box-folder 1 / 44)
    - Insurance, 1955 January 26 - February 1 (Box-folder 1 / 45)
    - Inter-Governmental Cooperation, 1955 February 3 (Box-folder 1 / 46)
    - Judiciary, 1955 January 13 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 47)
    - Labor and Compensation, January 28 - February 2, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 48)
    - Liquor Control, 1955 January 27 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 49)
    - Military Affairs, 1955 January 18 - March 1 (Box-folder 1 / 50)
    - Oils and Leases, 1955 January 19 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 51)
    - Public Health and Safety, 1955 January 24 - February 23 (Box-folder 1 / 52)
    - Public Lands, 1955 January 24 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 53)
    - Public Utilities and Industry, 1955 February 5-21 (Box-folder 1 / 54)
    - Relief and Social Security, 1955 January 31 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 55)
    - Rules, 1955 January 10 - February 23 (Box-folder 1 / 56)
    - State Boards, Offices and Buildings, 1955 January 13 - February 28 (Box-folder 1 / 57)
    - Taxation, 1955 January 19 - February 26 (Box-folder 1 / 58)
  - Senate Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-7, 10-19, 22-26, 28, 31-44, 46, 48-60, 64-69, 73-74, 76-81, 84-96, 98-99, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 59)
    - Bill nos. 102-119, 121-125, 127-128, 130-132, 135, 138, 145-151, 153-160, 164-174, 177-180, 182, 184-186, 189-193, 195-196, 198-199, 201-203, 205-208, 210, 211-212, 215, 217, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 60)
  - Senate Joint Resolutions
    - Bill no. 2, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 61)
  - Senate Memorials
    - Regarding the death of William R. Allen, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 62)
  - Senate Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-12 (re report of the Committee on Federal Aid to Agriculture; jurisdiction within reservations; construction of Yellowtail Dam; Continuation of 1948 Sugar Act; federal aid for primary and secondary highway systems; application of social security to self-employed ranchers and farmers; emergency funds for Indian relief and welfare; addition of U.S. Highway 2 to the national system of state highways; provision of payments or grants in lieu of taxes on non-taxable Indian lands; control of spruce budworm; increase in acreage allotments for premium high protein wheat; and construction of Libby Dam), 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 63)
  - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
    - 42nd Legislative Day, 1955 February 13 (Box-folder 1 / 64)
- Miscellany
  - List of members of Senate Mines and Mining Committee, 1955 (Box-folder 1 / 65)